welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
we're gonna stop here
perfect well hello everyone
welcome to the stone the still has a
place to dialogue and cohere about what
matters most with a nice edge of this
moment I'm Phillip Chen I'm going to
emcee for today and I'm super excited to
have forced at this door
he's one of the life-like human that I
trust the most in the world
he's a polymath philosopher writer
researcher craftsman a whole bunch of
things but his most original work is his
insightful work has been in metaphysics
so the study of what is was the nature
of being what is the nature of knowing
and what it means to make good choices
his fundamental work the eminent
metaphysics has influenced many many
people know Jordan Hall down Spartanburg
are it also has a lot of kindred
thoughts with other stoic guests like
Dave Snowden exacts time Justin Harris
so really force doesn't make many public
appearances so we're really in for a
treat today using me sharing his
thoughts on human collaboration so
what's likely to happen for today just
as a brief kind of agenda so you can
orient yourself is it's gonna be tough
for forceful talk boat for fifteen to
thirty minutes and afterwards there'll
be a Q&A will he'll be answering your
questions so how the Q&A will work just
briefly is if you have a question you
can write in the chat box and then I'll
call on you to unmute and ask your
question this whole session will be
recorded so if you want me to read your
question just indicated when you write
down Sam without further ado I want to
pass it to Forrest talk about human
collaboration good evening it's
wonderful to be invited to this forum
and I've been actually looking forward
to this and definitely a lot of new
faces and some people that I know and
definitely glad to be speaking on these
matters
so what I was going to talk about
tonight or what I'm thinking what I'm
spending a lot of time thinking about in
my life so the kind of work that I've
been engaged with these last few years
basically has been centered around what
we would think of as chronic problems
particularly a big hairy audacious
chronic problems the kind of things that
are complicated to such an extent that
we really couldn't expect a single
person to learn every aspect of that
problem in a lifetime or that really
requires a broad variety of points of
view to even get a sense as to what be
an appropriate response and so this this
kind of problem space shows up in things
like existential risk things that can be
basically really impactful on us on a
civilization scale and what would we be
calling the long-term conscious
sustainable evolution ie what kinds of
things would create sort of a holistic
thriving on the part of the planet
ourselves as species and an ecosystem in
that context so in effect you know when
we when we look at the kinds of
government systems that exist in the
world today they're mostly designed to
respond to acute situations hospitals
and police and and military and the
kinds of congressional process to
judicial process and so on for the most
part are oriented around dealing with
things as they come up and so in effect
there's a there's there's a need for us
to address protocols because as we
develop technology to a larger large
extent or we utilize it more in a larger
portion of the world essentially deploys
computers and cell phones and
automobiles and all the infrastructure
that goes with all that stuff that in
effect there's this sort of rebalancing
that is needed in the relationship
between man-machine and nature so in
effect we need to be able to think about
problems in ways that are much more
long-term than say the next quarterly
report or the kinds of things that would
be done in a single election cycle so in
effect there's a there's a phenomenon
here of you know for the toolkit that
civilization gives us the kinds of ways
in which it addresses problems that
exist
obviously this toolkit solves a problem
it's used and it's the problem the
problem solved but if we had like a sort
of collection of problems and some of
them are solved by the toolkit and some
of them are not then over time there's
this residual class of problems that the
toolkit just doesn't address and so
problems in that class have been
accumulating for some time and it
becoming quite important so in address
to that most of the work that I've been
doing has been thinking about okay well
what's gonna be needed in order to
actually address those that kind of
problem ie things that are very chronic
very complicated
what sort of facilities and resources
would we need to have as a as a human
species to essentially be able to
address things like that so one of the
things that we could start to do is we
could start to say okay well let's look
at it as a coordinate coordinated action
problem like we have a group of people
that wants to solve this particular
issue and as as I'm sure most of you
know that's not actually the easiest
thing to do first of all because people
get involved in games of power there's a
lot of social dynamics that essentially
emerge in that kind of space that
actually makes it very difficult to do
the kind of problem solving exercises
that are needed to address these issues
we haven't as a as a species really come
up with a very good collective
brainstorming so system capacity you
know that can really address long term
issues so in effect what we what we end
up doing is we start to say okay well
insofar as we are looking at the
relationship between man-machine in
nature then there's a kind of thing of
okay well how do we think about
communities of action how do we think
about communities of sense-making
and so immediately we start to notice
that without sense-making without some
capacity to know what needs to be done
that even if we had a really effective
way of responding you know some sort of
so metaphorically we can talk like a
race car right so I could have a race
car that has a really efficient engine
it's really powerful it's got a really
nice paint job it looks looks good fuel
efficient and all those kinds of things
but if the car is going in the wrong
direction it just doesn't matter so in
effect there's a there's a sense of
needing to know what to do in order to
be able to guide any process that would
effectively inform collective action so
as a result of again just sort of
thinking about it that way
I've come to focus a lot on sense making
how do groups of people collectively
make sense of the world to to even just
enable individual action let alone
collective action so a lot of the work
that I've been doing recently is focused
on sense making specifically the kinds
of things that would be needed for sense
making and what sort of orientations
would be needed to support that so so
that's kind of like again just orienting
sort of direction the next sort of layer
of this comes into the space of okay so
if we have a community of people say a
town or or some some motivated group
what would be the ways in which that
sense making process would happen so in
other words if we're going to put some
sort of system in place or some sort of
capacity in place or or to create
capacity in that group then we need to
start thinking about the kinds of
agreements that would be in place to do
that but that didn't immediately lets us
encourages us to start thinking about
well what is the infrastructure that
supports agreements if I'm looking at a
business for example you can think of a
business entity as being like a
collection of agreements it's a you know
it's a employment contracts and vendor
agreements and rent agreements and and
all sorts of legal documents one way or
another that collectively form the
corporation but most people you know
while the state might describe it that
way most people don't think of a
corporation as being a collection of
agreements I think it actually as a
collection of people and people that
have capacities you know you might think
about tools and capital and things like
that but basically without some sort of
relationship structure network of
relationships then you don't really have
a company you don't really have a
community so in effect when we start
thinking about the relationship between
the network of agreements and the
network of relationships becomes very
clear that the capacity to have
agreements in in culture or in in
society in any organization depends upon
the robustness of the relationships if I
make an agreement with my neighbor to
maintain the fence for the
six years but they move away in three
months then the validity of the
agreement just isn't that good in other
words we we really only have capacity to
trust the agreements to the degree that
we trust the relationships and so when
we start thinking about okay well what
kinds of network of relationships do we
need in order to really think about this
as a as a capacity building for
sense-making then then we start to
immediately start thinking about
communications you know when I think of
a relationship with another person I'm
thinking about all of the communications
that I've had with them all the complete
history of our interactions and you know
particularly for close relationships I
might also think about the potential
communications I could have all kinds of
things we could do together
so in other words if you treat the you
know just every moment of time you know
every time I see them under seating
messages in the form of what I see but
also what they say and and so on and so
forth
that in effect that the content of
relationship is that is the total
experience of the of the communication
that I have with each person and it
within the community so then we start to
think about sense making in terms of
communication practices rather than
thinking about it in terms of agreements
or relationships directly we're now
talking about what are the kinds of
communication practices that creates the
capacity for sense-making particularly
capacity for sense-making for big hairy
audacious problems because those are
kind of problems that we don't have the
capacity to deal with very well
currently so you know this is basically
just kind of giving an overview of some
of my thinking around these things and
the idea here is I said if we're going
to actually work on the kinds of
communications that enable sense making
when we start to notice that certain
things are really helpful we really want
to get into what is the fundamental
nature of what allows for genuine
communication to actually create sense
making as a result in other words in
what way does reason or rationality or
perspective or insights or an awareness
of principles or wisdom results from the
very nature of the dialogue process
very nature of the collaboration process
so in that sense I found myself becoming
quite interested in collaboration as
practice
and as a kind of art form as well I
began over the over this time to really
come to appreciate conversation as an
artful and dialogue is an apt one you
know really think about wit and the
degree to which those kinds of
interactive processes emerge and evolve
a capacity for perspective and insight
and things like that
so you know again connected to this this
other body of work the metaphysics was
mentioned I was I was given certain
tools to think about this so for example
one of the insights that came from from
thinking about relationships and
communication theory and information
theory and things like that is a
communication as a process happens when
each participant grants to the other
participant so scientists in a
one-to-one conversation with another
person that each person grants to the
other the right to speak the right to be
understood and the right to know that
they have been understood and these are
just given they're not they're not
demanded you can't you can't ask for
these things but you can you can give
them voluntarily to your teary pardon
and hopefully your partner will also
give those same three rights to you and
and when that handshake happens when
each party gives the three to the other
then communication in this true sense
becomes possible so in effect there's a
there's a kind of reciprocity that goes
on but it's not a reciprocity of quid
pro quo of this for that it's a kind of
mutual gifting the the sort of autonomy
that Burning Man would sort of encourage
so it's in that process that we can now
actually have some sort of reciprocity
that allows for collective emergence a
kind of embodiment of wisdom to be
shared between two people in the debt
that sharing process essentially emerges
a new phenomenon of wisdom because you
can see from two points of view so that
the idea of perspective taking starts to
become really important so that's why
you know to grant the other the right to
be understood and for them to know that
they've been understood is to
essentially to enable a capacity of
something that in some fields is called
phase parallax so for example we have
two eyeballs right and if I just cover
up one I'm gonna see a two-dimensional
field of vision if I basically have both
and what's happening is that these two
two dimensional fields of information
are being combined and in my brain and
this happens for everybody that has two
eyeballs basically that work well and
that the emergence of a third dimension
like because I see two slightly
different perspectives I can effectively
identify how far away something is and
it's it partly by the separation in
other words if they were in the same
place then they wouldn't be able to see
from two different perspectives in such
a way to get a sense by the
triangulation from the two eyes how far
away it is so in other words if I just
take and add two to two dimensional
fields of information on top of one
another I'm still going to have a two
dimensional field of information but if
I integrate the information then I'm
going to get this third dimension I'm
going to end up with this new capacity
that emerges out of the combination of
the two points of view so in effect when
were when we're looking at communication
as a process it's not so much that we're
just trying to advocate our point of
view to the other person that the other
person's trying to convince us that
their point of view we're really
interested in doing is is that each
person is trying to see through the eyes
of the other while also being able to
see through their own eyes or see
through the experience and then the
narrative of the other person as well as
the narrative that they themselves have
so that through the synthesis not just
the addition but the synthesis of those
two perspectives that effectively a new
dimension of insight becomes possible
everybody in the world has a good story
they have the story of their lives which
is essentially a unique perspective we
all walk our own unique path and so in
effect what happens is that by being
able to see from two perspectives I can
gain an insight into a situation through
the depth of their experience combined
with the depth of my experience so
there's a skill there to actually join
those two capacities to do the
perspective taking necessary to be able
to genuinely walk in the other person's
shoes without losing memory of my own
state and then obviously if the other
person is doing that as well then then
there's an insight to de gain and now we
can start to share those insights so a
meta level of insight becomes possible
and and so it sits in the experience of
this that we really begin to develop a
deep love for conversation deep love for
dialogue there's a there's a there's an
opening that happens there one of the
other things that the metaphysics was
given an awareness of is that joy is
when there is a is an experience it's a
feeling that we have when we perceive an
increase in the potentialities available
to self so when I can perceive these
deepenings these new these new insights
then all of a sudden new possibilities
emerge and that's usually a joyous
experience because that opening and
expansiveness of possible perspectives
and therefore possible actions is
something that we experience in a very
beneficial way there's a visit there's a
moment of joyousness in that process and
so as a result there's of worthwhile
Natur engaging in the practice for its
own sake not just for the outcome that
it could produce so you know one of the
things that has been sort of noticed
along the same lines is that when we
look at language language has basically
three three aspects of how it's
expressed some thinking from a
linguistics perspective particularly we
can use language to make statements such
as
I'm doing at this moment on making
certain claims I'm saying eh this is
some of the things I'm thinking about
this is some of the ways and thinking
about them and those claims could be
evaluated in various ways as may be
helpful or not but we could issue
directives I could say something to
somebody and say hey could you please
get me a glass of water or you know
would you shut the door or well you know
we can give instructions to
and then the third thing that we can do
with language is that we can ask
questions and so when we when we
basically think about the kinds of roles
that statements have and the various
characterization so at this point we
have three kinds of things we can do
with language the three sort of basic
coordinating intentionality x' that sort
of subsume the space of all the
different things you can do with
language at least in one perspective
then then we can start to say okay what
is the wall of identity what is the wall
of relationship how do we think about
the dynamics of what happens in exchange
when when one person makes a statement
to the other versus when one person
makes a demand of another or when one
person asks the question of another and
and so when we when we look at that from
the point of view of identity and egoic
structures and things like that you
notice that when a person makes a claim
they have a little bit of their own
identity tied in but if they are saying
acts and so if a person challenges what
they say then then you know there's
gonna be a desire to defend that or to
you know try to convince people that
it's true and stuff like that
if I'm basically asking somebody to do
something there's also kind of echoic
structure tied up in that in a sense of
you know I'm trying to exercise
authority or power or something like
that to to convince someone to shift
their behavior on my behalf or maybe
even on their behalf obviously you can
ask people to do things for their own
benefit as well but there's a there's a
capacity here where when we think about
the relationship between self-identity
in the communication process and we
think about questions we notice
questions are actually a little
different in terms of their egoic
identifications and statements and
directives when we're asking a question
we're basically not so ego eclis tied up
into it I mean it can be I mean for some
people there's this sort of social
cultural thing that you know to ask a
question is to reveal a kind of weakness
or to then you know to admit that you
don't know something is some cases you
know socially resisted a bit but
ultimately when we when we think about
this in a more transcultural way or we
will sort of factor out that the
cultural aspects but just looking at the
Agila castex it's usually less the case
that there is an egoic identification
when asking question there's a kind of
intellectual humility that goes with
that and so if we're if really
encouraging sense making fundamentally
then you know when we're when we're
looking at this phase parallax process
of how do we gain insight and so and so
forth well immediately if two people are
basically asking a question and both of
them are in inquiry about something then
then rather than you know coming up
against one another as would be the case
with a statement or with with directives
they turn and they they're both sitting
side by side and they're both looking
out into the world to try to figure out
what's going on so if the if the
emphasis is sense-making and the
emphasis is of developing insight in
this phase parallax process of being
able to perceive from multiple
perspectives or to be able to perceive
questions from multiple dimensions
therefore it becomes kind of a really
important exercise so in that sort of
sense I was led to sort of explore this
phenomenon called ephemeral due process
which is how do we take small groups of
people and create a kind of context in
container for them to explore questions
to essentially engage and an alternative
dialogue process where we are
effectively looking at how do we gain
insights about something that matters
something that's important how do we
engage the meaning seeking capacities
that we're all born with and to to sort
of utilize that in service to community
problem solving community sense making
so on one hand you know we're looking at
questions as part of the dynamic we're
looking at insight looking at phase
parallax looking at perspective taking
and that the kinds of things that would
facilitate high quality conversation and
developing a series of techniques about
how to encourage people and teach people
how to engage in this in this sort of
dialog process so that represents
essentially a body of work that's
currently being engaged within that work
we're actually seeking support to
continue to do but the main thing is is
that there's a there's a need to sort of
think about this in
to scale to because it's not just you
know how do we help people who already
want to be in conversation to solve a
problem to to encourage them to do so in
a genuine way that actually can work on
the kinds of issues the big hairy
audacious problems associated with
things like existential risk and things
of that matter so you know in one hand
we can rely a little bit on the
evolutionary propensity that we all have
to seek meaning to see patterns to to
look for things that are interesting
even the most rudimentary conversations
and they walk up to one of your friends
and you say have you seen any good
movies lately you know we're using the
sense making capacity that the other
person has their perspectives to sort of
identify you know what are interesting
movies what things stood out for them
what things did they think we're
particularly good or particularly
interesting and worthwhile as a desert
we could say entertainment but but an
experience to have and so you know if we
if we know what our friend is like and
what they like and and so on so forth
then we can gain a perspective that it
essentially allows us to have more
meaningful experiences in our lives more
interesting and worthwhile experiences
so that the sort of wisdom seeking
capacity is still kind of happening in
the background regardless but anyways if
we if we're looking at it from the point
of view of you know what is the
intentionality so remember we mentioned
egoic structures a minute ago and we're
saying okay well if we're actually
looking to solve big hairy audacious
problems and we're still wanting to sort
of avoid the entanglements that could
arise when you know large groups of
people collect together the power
structures that didn't end we emerged we
need to actually start looking at sort
of evolutionary dynamics that
essentially result in human behavior
like what kinds of things like our
built-in that we can utilize to
essentially do sense making what kinds
of propensity is exist and and so we
kind of you know we need to understand
the human condition really really well
to do work in this space and for several
reasons one of them is that obviously
you know the human evolutionary pattern
drives a lot of our behavior drives a
lot of the biases and our thinking and
so on so forth but it also creates the
kind of motivations and the motivational
base is supposed to engage in these
kinds of activities so there's there's
good things to know and other things
that we need to be able to work around
and and and also a kind of recognition
that while we can't necessarily change
the human condition we can work with it
and so in effect you know when we're
looking at the relationship between
man-machine and nature and was
essentially observing that and Daniel
has talked about this a bit you know in
some of his podcasts and things then
Daniel and Jordan I'm basically not
trying to repeat things that they've
already said simply because you know
we've been collaborating for some time
and they've taken a fair bit of this
content into the world already but the
idea here is is that when we're looking
at how do we essentially solve big big
difficult problems that are that are
very chronic you need a sort of
communication process that can work at
scale without becoming entangled in the
kind of biases and issues the the power
asymmetry structures that essentially
emerge directly out of a relationship
between machine process and human
process so for example when you look at
evolutionary systems and ecosystems in
particular conflict occurs in a context
and the overall system itself is
actually very much more cooperative
there are certain things that occur in
nature that are deeply deeply
cooperative processes they're not
necessarily obvious you know when we
look at a system it's easier to perceive
the conflict than it is to perceive the
cooperation and there's there's
metaphysical reasons and why that's the
case
having largely to do with the very
nature of the process itself if there's
you know an interruption of flow and
you're gonna perceive where that
interruptions happening because it's
creating a sort of barrier of sorts and
that barrier becomes an object that
makes it possible to proceed it whereas
things are flowing easily then you can
see through them they become transparent
there's a lot more I can say about those
dynamics but I just want to summarize
roughly here so anyways the idea here is
is that cooperation is
not only present and hard to see but
it's but it's actually the sort of
context in which ecosystems essentially
that the ecosystem creates this this
cooperative process and if there are
interest reasons conflict or entrust
species conflicts that occur you know
for a mate selection or things like that
it's held in the larger container of the
ecosystem in the ecosystem itself is
autopoietic to a large degree whereas
when we look at machine process machine
process doesn't presume a larger
cooperative context and so as a result
when we are orienting raw machine
process the the nature of the asymmetry
of power distributions that machine
technology creates that's my clock going
on in the background over there
anyways that when we when we look at you
know essentially a larger and larger
proportion of machine usage then
effectively what happens is is that the
co-operative context of the ecosystem
becomes too stabilized I'm not just
talking about issues associated with
pollution I'm actually talking about the
kinds of things that emerge access to
risk fundamentally daniel talks a lot
about the generator functions of
existential risk and we can talk about
the kind of problem dynamics there's
lots of different ways to describe
fundamentally what are the nature of the
problems and and and lots of different
ways to describe it each of which is
comprehensive with the political within
its own context I'm not going to try to
go into all those statements here you
know the three of us have worked on that
issue for some time and it actually come
to some pretty concise descriptions but
the idea here is is that we want to
basically be able to shift the
relationship from the relationship in
the relationship between man machine and
nature because if we don't then what
ends up happening is is that this
destabilization of you know man's
relationship to nature the man's
relationship to machines and machines
relation to nature such that nature
suffers so effectively the 25 minutes
okay
I'm gonna try to wrap up and so
essentially what happens is is that the
the dynamic of cooperation that nature
and ecosystems normally have needs to be
risa ported so in other words rather
than having
machines and service demand we need
machines to be in service to nature and
to some extent man service to machines
so that it can be in service to nature
so the nature can provide the kind of
ecosystem necessary to support life ie
our own included with that we have as a
species with someone naive impression
that machines should serve us and
unfortunately that that isn't working
very well because of this ecosystem
destabilization issue so bringing it
back down to a kind of human context
when we're looking at what is the
relationship between the end machine
we're wanting to basically compensate
for the biases and beings have using the
right level of technology
unfortunately the level of technology is
currently deployed is actually way
extensive way way way beyond what is
needed in order to essentially correct
for the biases in human process we want
to essentially rework the relationship
between those so that human beings can
actually be in communication do the
sense-making so that they can actually
be genuinely responsive to the ecosystem
in a holistic way one last point that I
would I would like to make in this
context which is actually pretty
important is that again for similarly
evolutionary reasons we tend to think
about communication as being in service
to our own ends to our other needs much
the same way that we think of machinery
as being in service to our own needs so
in effect if we look at you know again
functions of communication from an
evolutionary perspective we see it can
be used for mate selection survival
orientation process of one sort or
another in intergenerational knowledge
transfer in effect what happens is that
because of evolutionary process in
particular cultural process in the West
a lot of historical reasons which I
don't think I've time to get into there
has been this great preponderance for us
to think about communication as being an
individual process if if it was
something that was to be in service to
one's own and one's own you know benefit
basically and really if we're going to
work on civilization scale issues if
we're going to work on existential risk
issues we actually need to think about
our communication processes being in
service
that larger need ie thinking about
things from an ecosystem perspective or
from a species perspective or from a
community perspective as a primary
orientation rather than thinking about
it as being for one's individual benefit
or for one's local family or for one's
just you know immediate context so in
other words a lot if you basically look
at the internet and you just grab a
sample of say a million communications
and then you wait them on the basis of
is the orientation from which this the
person making the utterance the author
of the statement is doing so for their
own personal benefit or for some
expected benefit in the future to accrue
to them as a result of making that
statement you'll feel you'll see that
the overall preponderance is in favor of
that rather than speaking on behalf of a
larger group or all things like that not
to say that that doesn't happen you know
obviously you know people do take
altruistic actions you know they they
speak up for the benefits of their
community and they do speak up for the
benefits of things like you know social
welfare and things like that
but that in effect we look at the
preponderance of behavior it's largely
on the side of the individual benefit
and only occasionally on side of
altruistic benefit so in one sense to to
really do sense making at a community
level we need to ship that balance and
have it be a little bit more on the on
the community benefit side that needs to
be done with a certain amount of just
you know discernment however because you
know people that operate just all
touristical e can be taken advantage
there's a free rider problem there's a
lot of issues where people can extract
value from that practice and essentially
benefit on a personal level from from
essentially extracting value from the
Commons that is created by those actions
however if we if we think about the
dynamics of communication well and
deeply enough and we think about the
relationship between you know again that
triangle of man-machine in nature in an
appropriate way then it does become
possible for us to compensate for those
kinds of issues and this is largely what
has been on my mind what I've been
thinking about these last couple of
years so I guess with that summary I'll
leave it at that seeing as how I
probably consumed way too much time
already and I'll just leave it open to
questions and see what people are
interested to know
alright thanks for the nice overview I'm
just gonna say real quickly how the Q&A
works again we are into fielding
questions in the chat box and then I
will call upon you if so would you think
you would unmute and ask your question
obviously this is recorded so if you
want me to read your question just
indicate it and I will write it down
oh please indicate when you read it down
so yeah I'm gonna probably start with a
question myself yeah I loved that you
took started with these big hairy
problems and then brought them down to
communication is something that we can
do and then moved into EGP which is your
something you're currently working on
and they talked a little advice I I want
to ask you a question around the social
dynamics that you mentioned earlier or
power and corruption and how it kind of
each EP thinks to thought that that's
the question that's been on my mind that
I want to ask you in the projects that
we work with but also I think you'd open
up a lot of potential other questions as
well so the the desire to seek Christy
Asian to seek a certain amount of
influence over one's environments to to
effectively do these these are innate
things I mean it's not you know it's not
the intention here to say that this is
fundamentally bad but in certain
contexts you know it can be it can be
overextended so the the the aspect of
technology effectively leverages these
these sort of relative power over
seeking capacities on the part of
individuals it makes the the wealth
inequality distribution much more any
unequal you know fundamental metrics
like that and again there's lots of
evidence to talk about and to support
these perspectives but the idea here is
is that if we're doing sense making we
need to not have those kind of dynamics
drive the process so in effect there's a
it's like if we're looking at my
existential risk issues then rather than
mate selection which is a relative
communicative basis where
I'm talking about things on a survival
basis which is an absolute foundation so
in other words to survive you only need
to actually solve the problem you don't
need to be something better than the
next guy standing next to you so the
difference between good enough to solve
the problem versus better than everyone
else in your particular group you know
in order to quote-unquote win really
makes a huge difference if we're if
we're looking at relative relationships
as the basis of what we mean by success
or what we mean by win-win then that
that's just not actually the correct
formulation of how to think about this
so in in a sense when we're saying
win-win solutions we're talking about
win-win in the sense of ultimate
underlying values I need the idea is is
that values aren't something that's held
on the part of an individual it's
something that is held by essentially a
collection of individuals meaning making
meaningfulness itself it's not something
which is a an individual action either
purposes can be individual but meaning
is an interpersonal phenomenon I can you
know make up a word and say this word is
defined as that thing but unless other
people essentially sort of go along with
that then then it doesn't become part of
language so you know in a sense there's
there's there is a sort of idea here
that nobody owns language there's no
identity structures attached to language
particularly I mean there may be you
know some you know like the French
culture for example has a lot of esteem
with language but fundamentally language
is still a shared phenomenon as part of
the culture rather than part of a
particular person's identity so and so
in that particular sense when we're
looking at you know what are the kinds
of dynamics that facilitate sense making
we're saying okay well first of all we
want to have less asymmetry in the
communication process we want
individuals to be talking to one another
enough many-to-many relationship rather
than broadcast such that you have one
person speaking and lots of people
listening and there's not a symmetry and
the co relatedness the person is doing
the broadcast very rarely gets to
understand the points of view of the
people that he's talking to and this is
a loss right I mean it's it's not it's
not actually communication and
sense that is needed so in that
particular sense what were what we're
really looking to do is it's not so much
say that you know the kinds of
communication patterns that people would
engage with in the business world along
is just as simply said you need to
create a different context and so one
aspect of that is not to have broadcast
but essentially to have small groups not
to have it you know be defined in terms
of statement making or directive making
but actually defined in terms of
questions to have it be much more about
perspective taking rather than about
agreements and so there's there's a lot
of specific dynamics that are kind of
built into the EGP process some of them
you know they look obvious on the
surface but there's there's actually a
lot of subtlety involved in that it's
it's there's a there's a tremendous
richness of thinking that has gone into
this and that and not just on my part is
if there's a lot of people that are
collaborating on this now so in effect
there's a there's there's a real
richness of what on the surface looks to
be simple practices but the emphasis is
not so much in terms of simplicity as it
is clarity so the the clearer the
communication process of them the more
in which we can essentially have people
really sink into one another in a
collaborative way the more likely that
the emergence of solutions the big hairy
audacious problems become possible
just looking through all the questions
right now so I would like to start off
with a question from Reed can you unmute
as for sure can you hear me yeah thanks
for doing this forest so I was wondering
you mentioned those three principles for
productive sense making dialogue and I
was wondering just what other kind of
low-hanging fruit there might be like
nonviolent communication or steel
Manning or other kinds of elements that
we could introduce that would be
productive oh there's a lot nonviolent
communication is a good start when I
look at the nonviolent communication
thing I noticed that there's a couple of
elements that I would add one of them is
a kind of affirmation to really
basically you know connect to the other
person to say hey there's there's
something really beautiful there so the
validation piece is important and then
the question-asking piece there really
wasn't something explicitly said in the
sort of four core elements of
non-violent communication that it
allowed for inquiry to really be a thing
this and those are minor things and idea
here is that you know those are those
that's that's one slice of good practice
another good practice is to sometimes be
aware or to to really focus on the
awareness around what we would have is
an action bias so many times people will
ask how do I do something and while in
in in in in in the world where we're
living that's actually a very good bias
to have to be able to execute and solve
problems sometimes it's important for us
to stand back and ask them what question
what does success look like how would we
recognize it okay so in other words the
the what part of the question drives the
how but if we just go directly to and we
lose sight of the of the why question
and the what question particularly the
what question then then to some extent
we actually might be as I mentioned with
the metaphor of the car we might have a
grand car
be a racecar with absolute complete
capabilities but but if it's solving the
wrong problem then it just isn't isn't
the right thing so in effect the the
other principle that I think has been
mentioned I believe this one Jordans you
know the Omega principle ie presume that
the other person has something
worthwhile to say that they're they're
doing their best to to communicate
something that's meaningful and
important I mean this is true even in an
adversarial context that you know that
the values that the other person has is
is there's a grain of truth and whatever
it is that they're valuing and that
there's a there's a sense of there's no
fundamental value conflicts I mean we
sometimes get into this perspective of
well I value a and the social person
values B but you can actually - you both
a and B there's no mutual exclusivity
that's required to UM you know unless
people are really trying to construct it
that particular but that really doesn't
happen that way as a as a natural
phenomena it happens as a constructive
one that effectively values naturally
can co-occur so there's a there's a
sense here of you know communications
hard like in any given moment the amount
of vocal bandwidth that I have to convey
ideas is about 42 bits per second it's
just not very much you know when we're
looking at computers and stuff like that
that is you know speaking back and forth
with one another eight megabytes per
second or gigabytes per second it's like
you know the the actual available inter
brain communication bandwidth is
appallingly low and the bandwidth of
consciousness itself as a phenomena is
not very high either so you know for us
to to really leverage this wonderful
nervous system that we have in the
miraculous list of life we need to
actually lie on an unconscious process
quite a bit and so in effect there's a
there's a need for us to take some
things for granted with the other in the
sense of really working with them to
search out the meaningfulness you know
when any one person says something to
someone else it's very easy to do this
stupid obvious thing to point out the
false parts the parts that you don't
agree with the parts that don't make
sense but it really requires a much
higher level of skillfulness to
basically say okay I want to reach
through the inside of all that and find
out what is the grain of truth that the
that is really genuinely important it's
genuinely insightful that really speaks
to meaningfulness or values or the
sacred and so you know when we when we
give that sort of willingness to hear
the inside of the message to really seek
out the parts that are the beautiful
principles underneath it all then the
communication process can move forward
and far more dynamic way than what
otherwise be the case and and and
another principle is is basically to
recognize when you know we're looking at
an adversarial conversation versus a
mutual cooperative one I mean a lot of
times people I mean at least for myself
I mean we could we either get into the
habit of assuming cooperation which I
tend to do or we're into the habit of
assuming adversary on this which I know
some of the people do and and and again
it's not right wrong here but it's it's
a little bit of a thing of if it's a if
you're making the wrong assumption as to
the to the nature of the conversation
and then you're not communicating very
well and this is basically to observe
that both have their place you know for
if we're looking at a jury trial type of
situation where it's important for us to
cut to the right answer and people's
lives depend upon the sort of sense
making process that a jury trial is you
know you want all of the sensing
capacities to to be engaged and then
dependent yes it's an adversarial
process but on the other hand you know
to really look at it with enough
dimensions or really to identify what is
what is the deep truth of what's
happening here's is actually really
important sometimes you know the the
adversarial conversation provides a way
for the keeper values to be identified
and opinion to be brought forward in a
productive way hopefully we have that
shift from an adversarial context to a
cooperative one but if we mistake which
conversation were in or what the
intentions are what matters to the other
person because we're not paying
attention or we just presume that they
don't have anything interesting to say
then then we kind of miss the point
so you know in that situation I'm
basically looking at you know a lot of
different principles that sort of
involve things that would enable deep
communication to occur
you know getting into the kinds of
exercises that allow you to do
perspective taking on the part of the
other to really put yourself in the
shoes of the other that's a huge skill
and not very many people get into that
but on the other hand you know if
there's if there's something that you
want to do to essentially become a
better communicator that's that's that's
a by far strong thing to do where I am
but the question is essentially how do
you get groups of people who do not
engage when I think you might not have
the opportunity to engage one another
nevertheless to have more clear
communication that could lead to
something more generative
solutions-oriented but they might not be
exposed to one another to begin with I
might not have that invite to start well
I think that there's there's a lot of
work going on in this space I don't know
that I would be adding anything original
but you know to bring all the
stakeholders into the conversation and
to essentially help them to engage with
one another
there's a lot of human development stuff
that's it's really helpful so for
example you know people are in a
traumatized state and they don't have
any way of dealing with their own
personal trauma then then they're just
going to have a hard time communicating
at all so in effect there's a there's a
sense of you know how do we increase
individual health how do we how do we
help people to essentially you know
develop the skills of socialization that
would essentially allow them to
communicate well and deeply with one
another occasionally that means just
meeting needs you know make making sure
that needs are met but but in in you
know once once you get sort of passed
with the rudimentary kinds of things you
know creating an environment which is
essentially conducive to this process so
you might start with provisional
agreements for the meeting that is
actually happening after you've created
the invitation you might need to give
certain assurances to the people that
are coming into that context that they
are safe then that contact
specific ways you might need to
basically do things to ensure that other
people don't leverage the concept of
safety itself as the kind of weapon
you might want to get really good at
recognizing what weaponization is you
know what is weaponized communication
look like and how do you basically do
the kinds of practices that aren't about
that that effectively emerge from that
so you have to recognize what that looks
like
any anything that is essentially the use
of causation to suppress choices is is
gonna be somewhat suspect to not right
in that particular way so the idea here
is is that you know there's there's a
lot of different ingredients that all
need to work together in order to create
the context where people are actually
communicating with one another
fortunately the human biology provides
some support for this process but you
know given the the technology that's
involved and so on so forth des there's
a need for us to essentially become much
more skillful about these particular
things than we ever have as a species
previously or that nature has ever
needed to before for a lot of the
problems that we're looking at there's a
there's a need for us to be far more
discerning about these practices because
evolution hasn't prepared us for the
kinds of needs and demands that are
currently placed on the human species
vis a vis it's it's now technological
capabilities you know power of gods and
all that sort of thing so so at this
particular juncture just to try to sum
up an answer to your question first of
all it's not a single thing it's a whole
bunch of practices that all kind of work
together in concert and there's a lot of
really good work going on in this field
and so all I can really do at this point
is just give you there's kind of the
outlines of a summary to end off
potentially if are as I came across your
quote love is that which enables choice
love is always stronger than fear always
choose on the basis of love and I looked
you up thinking your
like at Ernst McKenna number two and I
was surprised to see yeah so I'm curious
where this came from if you wanted to
unpack that first sure well it's it's
it's it's a quote that that I put
together as what is the single most
succinct and useful in in a life sense
you know if I had to condense I mean
obviously I can't hold all of the things
that I've learned in life but but but if
I want to pick the single most useful
learning the single most useful wisdom
that that was really what came to mind
the idea of love is that which enables
choices partly a description of what
love is like how do we know that we are
being loving to another person what is
the litmus test that allows us to
distinguish between we think we're being
loving versus we're actually being cruel
or you know the other person says that
they love us but we're not feeling the
love and and and we might want to need
it or need a tool to understand why
there's a difference between what they
say they're doing what we're feeling so
in effect the idea behind love is that
which enables choice is essentially a
kind of it's not based upon the feeling
of love it's based upon the action what
does it mean to do it and so you know
one sort of parable that I that I
described to to convey this and give a
sense of it is that you know salmon in a
partnership with a woman and you know
I'm wanting her to feel love from me and
I was I'm wanting to enable her in her
life to realize her dreams to become
more fully and completely herself to
become the best and brightest and most
brilliant person she can be and in that
process of her becoming that then I can
know her better and I can understand the
miraculous of her life in it in a deeper
more felt sense and so in a way it's
that I'm not trying to make choices for
her because if I if I substitute her
choices with mine then I don't ever get
to experience who she is I'm not
actually in relationship to her I'm only
in relationship to the image of myself
that I've put in there
so in effect there's a there's some
really deep truths tied to this I mean
when we're looking at say child raising
for example you know when they're born
they have no capacity to choose on their
own part I mean they are they're
literally completely dependent on the
parents and then you know they get to
whatever adulthood is and they move out
or we die and at some point we can't
make any choices on their behalf and if
they're going to continue to live well
in life you know to continue to be
healthy human beings then we have this
sort of transition from at t0 of making
100% of our choices to you know T 100
and we're passing on and they're making
a hundred percent of their own choices
and there's this sort of gradation
between those two where in effect the
the intention here is not to make the
choices on behalf of the child forever
but to teach you how to choose well and
fully how to live well and fully how to
have wisdom in his choices that it can
be discerning about what's actually
right to do and then anything less than
that means that we've effectively
created a damaged human being that isn't
capable of living your own lives in a
complete way so this notion of
intergenerational knowledge transfer
this intergenerational capacity is a
hundred percent enabling it's it's not
for the benefit of the previous
generations completely for the benefit
of the receiving one and so in effect
what's happening is is that we we
recognize that that as a core idea is
the very meaning of what it means to
love our children you know when we look
at say government relationship you know
the state and the people the function of
our government is to protect the land
and the people and that's a basic
function I mean you know to some extent
there's that there's a need for that but
the idea here is is that if we want to
go beyond that if we want to go to the
land and the people that are thriving we
need to go beyond protection and just
making people feel safe we actually want
to go to the space of that the the
ecosystem that the the holistic health
and vitality of the people in the lander
is increasing the ecosystem is becoming
essentially a more robust more
meaningful space to live in and so even
in a sense we're seeing this notion of
enables choice right so it isn't just
you know that we want a minimal
government in the maximal market place
because neither of the
in this cases is adequate to some of the
problems were facing but we actually
need more than that and so in effect
there's a there's a recognition here
that the notion of love is that which
enables choice the life liberty and
pursuit of happiness
not just at an individual level but at a
community level at a species level and
an ecosystem level and that the the
notion of meaningfulness and sacredness
and so on and so forth is is not
something that's taking it's something
that's given
I think that's all I could say about
that right now awesome I think that's a
great way to end of the session thank
you very much for us for coming and
gracing us with your presence thank you
Peter for providing the space and giving
me the opportunity to emcee this session
and thanks for everybody for coming here
and showing up and asking all your great
questions yeah I think I personally
learned that love and friendship and
communications are the basis what we
need to do moving forward and yeah I
didn't want to say that they're plugged
one event for tomorrow roughly in the
subject how to win friends and influence
people during the minute crisis with
Kevin chrome tomorrow at 10:00 a.m. you
can sign up there I have the still
thought CA yeah that's it for tech 9 10
things Harry please thank you very much
listings thanks Forrest thanks everyone